this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
see radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society by IEEE software
Magazine online at computer.org software
hello and welcome to software
engineering radio this is your host
nikhil Krishna I have with me today John
davidos John leads the development for
the Neo Global development practice in
Seattle he previously worked at
Microsoft and he built the Microsoft
digital.net patterns and practices and
the.net architecture strategy groups he
also incubated Microsoft Azure when he
was at Microsoft John launched two
machine learning startups but more
recently he is a board member at the
global blockchain Business Council and
the founder and head of development at
ngd Enterprise focusing on Building
blockchain Development tools
John did his PhD work in machine
learning specializing in recurrent
neural networks so welcome to the show
John great pleasure to talk to you is
there something in your bio that I
missed that you'd like to add thank you
Nico thank you first of all I want to
say thank you for giving me this
opportunity thank you for giving me time
and thank you for the very kind
introduction no I think there was enough
in there so I will not add any more
thank you cool so the topic for today is
an interesting one it's about design
philosophies and as we discussed in your
introduction you've worked in pretty
large Enterprises on a pretty large
departments obviously there are design
philosophies that you have encountered
and embraced and one of the ones that
we're going to talk about today is some
of the design philosophies that
drive.net and Azure development so one
underlying pattern that you mentioned
was the concept of a loose coupling
which you said was one of the driving
patterns for the.net and zero platform
engineering perhaps for the audience
could you tell us what is loose coupling
in your mind and what is the advantage
of loose coupling and why you adopted it
in Microsoft certainly nickel yes thank
you I'll start with a little bit of
history historical timelines going back
perhaps to the mid to late 90s the early
days of service based or SOA
architectures and kind of the early very
early days possibly of even what you
might call cloud computing but that time
systems primarily were built in a
monolithic fashion monolithic meaning
sort of single system single app up and
down all the way what we were trying to
do with dotnet back in 99 early 2000
even long before before it was
called.net was to break away to first
chip away and break down these
monolithic systems the idea that systems
had to be so tight first chip away and
break down these monolithic systems
the idea that systems had to be so
tightly interconnected we believed and
of course now we know in retrospect you
know at that time it was very early in
the game that systems fundamentally
should be compositions of services
and the idea behind loose coupling was
that these Services should be autonomous
in their own right and and so if
services are autonomous in their own
right then what is an application an
application essentially becomes a
composition of one or more of these
services and so loose coupling as the
underlying principle almost the primary
principle if you will evolved in the
early days of dot net and of course it
continued to flourish through the Azure
incubation through the Azure development
as well so I would say much of the
Microsoft Dev platform and tools really
kind of shifted from a mindset
perspective away from monoliths to
autonomous services and of course loose
coupling you could say was the primary
design and Architectural philosophy okay
that's a great overview I appreciate the
historical context as well but in your
Endeavor or in your journey towards
becoming towards this particular
architecture could you talk about a
little bit about the challenges that you
might have faced or the pushbacks that
you might have faced and maybe also
comment about the constraints of the
system because every system obviously
has advantages and constraints right so
maybe you could talk a little bit about
that absolutely yes and I think you make
a very very good point the challenges
the constraints certainly but also the
enablers the challenges uh certainly you
know much in terms of the mental models
so much mind share so much engineering
so much developer share has had been
focused on single system monoliths that
even the idea the notion that somehow we
could build applications differently
that they could be compositions of
services was an alien concept and the
first I suppose the obvious question was
why
why do we even care and remember this is
about 20 20 plus years ago it was still
very early in the days of the internet
and the notion that entities would
collaborate would cooperate across the
internet was still lacking right and
that was kind of really the AHA as more
and more people saw the possibility
of connecting across and over the
Internet until then you know the
intranet was was the king and so you
could argue why do I care about Services
about loose coupling but once you broke
this sort of this abstraction that
connectivity was going to be over the
web
collaboration was going to happen over
the web and interconnectedness
interoperability was going to be a
driving imperative I would say that's
really what drove the the shift in terms
of challenges the interesting piece
nickel was there were some people who
took it overboard sort of went extremely
overboard and they said everything is a
service and everything right and so very
interesting I said think about it right
you had this sort of almost what you
might call a micro Services philosophy
everything every component
people assumed would become a service
and of course what happened then was
that composition becomes very expensive
right so there has to be some fine
balance between how you define the
boundaries of a service and so if the
assumption is that everything every
component even every object becomes a
service then the tax you pay in terms of
crossing boundaries in terms of Crossing
you know obviously between barriers of
trust right becomes quite expensive and
then the compositions of these Services
become you know sort of collapse under
their own weight and so we actually saw
in fact I remember I will not name names
but I remember you know many
applications within Microsoft but also
outside in terms of the industry where
people would call me and say John you
know this isn't working and Bitcoin
means I would say look you have 74
services
and for every customer use case if
you're going to invoke and compose
across 74 services this is not going to
work for you
right plus the extreme you know sort of
going overboard on the
but along the way this notion that
applications were not going to be your
father's application single system why
everything kind of lived within maybe
even one physical infrastructure right
right so loose coupling in terms of
services but the interesting piece also
nikhil was the realization the growing
understanding awareness that loose
coupling was also happening at the
hardware level right infrastructure
architecture versus application
architecture so loose coupling began at
the application architecture level but
eventually sort of moved into the
infrastructure space and so the notion
of abstractions
of virtualization which eventually led
to the idea of cloud computing also as
Loosely coupled abstractions of
infrastructure as opposed to
Applications right so in some sense you
could argue really this this notion of
coupling boundaries of barriers of
clarity of communication interaction
really drove the application
architecture
which is dot net but also the
infrastructure architecture which was uh
eventually azure
right so obviously you Illustrated a
very clear nicely the the challenges of
going overboard on one side right so
then the immediate question that comes
to you is and okay how how does one know
when you've gone overboard right what is
too much right so how do you develop
that sense in in this particular map no
that's a real really good question and
I'll tell you so this is what led to us
to develop this mental model this
abstraction that we called fiefdoms and
emissaries nickel right fifth jumps in a
Mysteries no very intentionally we used
archaic words archaic terminology right
what what is a fief term it's kind of
like a kingdom a medieval Kingdom what
is in a mystery in a mystery is a
messenger who helps to transmit messages
across fifth terms and and this notion
of thinking about fief terms was that
really services at the right level of
abstraction at the right level of
granularity ideally would be fief terms
meaning there had to be a need to
establish a boundary there had to be a
need to establish a border and they had
to be in need so think in terms of
messaging as the primary mechanism in
terms of communication and if really the
service abstraction did not qualify in
terms of this notion of a fiefdom
perhaps this was really a component or
maybe even an object but certainly not a
service and it helped kind of to
establish this this thinking around the
design patterns of like you said what is
the right level of granularity right and
of course there was still science and I
would say even today there is probably
no science but this notion of
established boundaries and the need for
boundaries like a moat you know fifth
terms had more surround them right does
your service really need the abstraction
of a moat then maybe perhaps it is a
service if not then you know maybe go
you know rethink and and is it really an
object or even a class for example right
correct yeah yeah that's a great thing
uh one of the ways that I've kind of
thought about this was around the idea
of bounded context which is a concept
that comes out of domain driven design
right yes yes very famous book from Eric
so obviously that is easy from a
business perspective so when you're
building a business application like for
example I'm building a application in
the logistics space the domain is kind
of clear you can say okay fine there is
this Con these are the concepts that are
part of that domain so you can kind of
try Okay create a context around I don't
know an airplane and context on a ship
or whatever right but I would imagine
that that's kind of different when it
comes to platforms like Azure and Dot
net right because you're kind of not
it's not it's not a business well it's
not an application per se it's something
that's supporting an application so how
did you kind of think about that for
example for azir how did you come up
with the domains for it so brilliant
question absolutely brilliant question
and you're right in terms of
domain-driven design and and the famous
book and sort of the the implications
right and the coronaries of how to think
about you know domain objects and such
so for us at least in terms of our
thinking I would say
I was influenced significantly by this
economist called cos nickel Myrtle Coast
he was a Nobel prize-winning Economist
and he he worked on this notion of the
theory of transaction costs
and the question he asked was why do
corporations exist why do business
entities exist why not just be a
free-for-all a true market where
everybody can transact with it with
anybody else as they choose to and his
thesis was that businesses are a sort of
corporate entities or things if you want
to call them congregate into one larger
entity in order to minimize the
transaction cost the cost of transaction
and where it became less expensive to
try to sort of Take It Outside then
clearly that piece would go off as
offshoring or Outsourcing or something
else right and so we had a very similar
economic model saying at what point do
the transaction costs
of spanning these boundaries really
cross the threshold and at what point
does it actually sort of still fall
within the threshold well we can say in
terms of abstractions so it's boundaries
this is acceptable and that's why
obviously at a very high abstraction
level compute versus storage or storage
versus bandwidth right all right so and
so on right of course that's a very
highly high level abstraction but you
can see yeah one more level and having
this economic lens because I would say
for the very first time this ability to
look at technology with an economic lens
I argue really happened because of
services because of loose coupling very
interesting approach yeah I mean I can
kind of see that right in terms of
economic cost of boundaries but
obviously there has to be kind of like a
measure or a way to kind of standardize
that because obviously when you're
talking about storage that's a different
dimension and then compute is a
different dimension bandwidth is a
different dimension right so so how was
the I'm sure there were probably some
kind of back and forth some some kind of
calibration required to to kind of get
to that common economic measure that
kind of reveals that right yes
absolutely you're absolutely right there
was a lot of debate a lot of discussion
a lot of how do we say it contention and
very hard contention as well because
clearly the infrastructure that we were
building the expectation was that
Millions you know tens of millions of
developers would be using it and so that
the flaws if there were any fundamental
flaws especially economic implications
could be quite expensive you know for
the application education developers on
top so you're right in terms of the lens
of of the economic cost also I would add
you know again this this mental model of
fiefdoms and emissaries really helped us
and you know if you will humor me I'll
kind of give you a story there as well
right sure sure thank you yeah so what
happened is that you know if you if you
buy into this notion of fief terms or
kingdoms and then emissaries right the
first question that we asked ourselves
is then the Scuff the things inside the
fifth term the data if you will how do
we think about the data and this led to
very interesting discussions debates on
what is Master data versus what is
reference data right versus what is
single user data I was the first big
debate so thinking about service
abstractions you know what kind of data
does the service possess or own right
the second thing was then if Services
own data then in terms of communicating
across victims across Services how do we
communicate and this led to the
discussion of messaging
right and what are the kinds of messages
obviously you know item potency comes in
you know what happens if you lose a
message what happens if you get it three
times the same message right and so
obviously if you have messages the third
one is you know what is the identity of
the messenger and so the claim what are
the claims the tokens that the messenger
has or processors to be able to transmit
the message right and the next thing
obviously then if you think about
messaging of course you could lose
messages there could be errors the
messenger could be corrupted maybe the
messenger could be
I guess not to be politically correct
but the messenger could be obviously
obfuscation and so on and so forth so
how do you ensure that you have a
certain level of error correcting
messaging which then led to business
process orchestration and conversational
messaging right so really it goes back
to I would say
perhaps this not very well known mental
model of victims and emissaries but
almost everything kind of really you
know sort of came out of that model like
I said in terms of data in terms of
identity the messaging the error
correction you know fault tolerance and
of course the business process
orchestration and more right and then we
found ourselves unable to precisely
delineate these components for a service
then the obvious implication was perhaps
this is not a service
right perhaps Yeah okay or here in terms
of how to articulate and maybe we should
go back once again to the drawing board
right that was kind of uh I'm giving you
a really sort of summarized perspective
but hopefully no absolutely yeah yeah
yeah so no but that that's that's very
useful and I think it's interesting to
me that the exercise of kind of thinking
about this as a kind of a fifth term or
a kingdom and kind of like looking at
the costs of the transactions going out
and inside the kingdom and trying to
figure out whether this is that exercise
in itself was so Illuminating in terms
of defining whether this is actually
truly a fiefdom or a service or not
right and that's that's a component or
even an object or a class or an object
or a class so in your experience does
this actually work across levels right
so we were talking in terms of very high
abstractions of compute and bandwidth
and storage and what have you but can
you then take this concept accept of
victims and emissaries and take it down
like within a service and say in the
organization of the service itself or
does that kind of like what is the kind
of like Breaking Point Beyond which
basically you probably is not a good
abstraction to use
that's a really really good question
it's a really I think it's a very
pragmatic question as well yeah and I'll
tell you sort of our debates and
discussions and the contention
the philosophy if I could use the word
philosophy that we took the kill was to
lead with service interfaces meaning
that much of the discussion the debate
the architecture if you will was focused
on the service interfaces why because
the thinking was that if we went with
the implementation first that we might
go too far into this to be able to
backtrack and then to fix things whereas
if we could agree on the service
interfaces then to your point like you
said we retain the flexibility to be
able to recompose or decompose service
interfaces so we could say for purposes
of expediency even though it might
violate you know sort of the
architectural principles for reasons of
expediency or for reasons of economic
costs we could collapse and say we're
going to have a meta service interface
that brings together these these sort of
you know second level of service
interfaces so that was the Compromise
you know we made right and the challenge
that I saw and sometimes still see in
practices that leading with the service
implementation does not give you that
flexibility to be able to roll back
right or to roll forward to be able to
correct whereas having the interfaces
you can make trade-offs and yes it might
not be Orthodox it might not be
pedantically correct in terms of the
philosophy or the principles however
like you said in Practical terms it gave
us the ability to make the thread
awesome and that's why when you look at
dot net or even Azure the aps you might
say what were those people thinking yeah
okay yeah I'm sure you heard that
no yeah sometimes not even a year right
sometimes even in in the dot net yes
yeah is there are some apis that are
like more intuitive than other apis
this guy thinking you know what was that
what was the logic right and he might
have been swearing as well but yeah
enough
yeah no it's it's a it's a great point
in the sense that business realities are
business realities and but so when you
say you define the interfaces and you
looked at the interfaces first does that
mean that once those interfaces were
defined they could not change or is that
more like okay we want to work outside
in but what happens if you go in and
then you realize okay some assumption
you made when you define the interface
is not working out and you really need
to change the interface yeah so again a
superb question naked absolutely I think
this is a this is a very very critical
question so two things I would say
firstly try to maintain this principle
of once you publish a service interface
stick with it do not change it but
version it if you have to so version it
has a 1.1 or a one point x or even a two
if you wish that's one being able to
maintain the Integrity of the contract
that that you have published right the
second thing was which I was I think
they're hinting a little bit earlier
being able to compose and have higher
level service interfaces and sometimes
lower level so still maintain the
Integrity as far as you can of what you
have published but for the reasons of
expediency and often actually for for
reasons of developer experience in terms
of syntactic sugar right to make life a
little bit more easier more productive
be able to have compositions meta
service interfaces but also the last
thing I would say is being able to
create proxies or agents right so those
were the the in some sense sort of a
second level Emissary for the service
where it enabled the consuming developer
to to be productive and to make life
easier for him or or her in the process
so we would say worsening you know being
able to compose up or down in terms of
the meta interfaces and then if those
didn't work to be able to publish
proxies or agents which obviously you
know while they were still working with
those published service interfaces could
and sometimes made life easier could you
kind of just kind of elaborate a little
bit or maybe Define what you mean by a
proxy or an agent because a proxy there
are different when you talk to different
people what a proxy is it's a it's a
different answer every time right so
your context what do you mean when you
say a proxy or an agent so no certainly
absolutely no you're right a proxy at
least for this discussion and certainly
what we had you know in terms of the
philosophy is this entity that that you
would communicate with in the place of
the actual destination in the place of
the actual you know sort of destination
service and so right in terms of a
mental model it was an emissary it's an
agent right it's an agent that you could
talk to and the agent could then
actually communicate to the uh the
service you know the the actual
destination right thinking about it
right a proxy be a rapper right and
sometimes in the tooling you know the
tools will basically look at an API like
a postman API and say okay I'll give you
a proxy and the proxy really what it
does is it gives you let's say a rust
you know sort of client library or a or
a c-sharp or or a python and so on
that's basically sort of the most I
would say lowest level proxy which is
just a sort of an API wrapper but the
processor agents the agents in
particular for us actually went into a
higher level of abstraction where for
instance in terms of being able to to
provide reference data to the consumer
right to store a local copy which
obviously was time stamped and verified
with the actual Service as an example
another one was in terms of messaging to
be able to do retries to be able to do
error handling to a certain extent where
in this case you could say and again I I
don't want to use the word intelligence
but certainly the proxy the agent has
more intelligence than just a plain
vanilla wrapper proxy right and that's
interesting because then those are truly
the emissaries because they have some
level of autonomy it's not just a
service having autonomy but the agent
itself also has some level of autonomy
and then truly truly then you have this
Emissary so I suppose you're right I use
the word Loosely and I shouldn't be
using it Loosely because proxies you
know sort of all the way through to
agents there is a difference in terms of
the level of intelligence but also the
level of autonomy and ideal right agents
truly are autonomous and so no you're
right and it's a very thank you thank
you for asking the question thank you
yeah yeah no no this is quite
fascinating so obviously one of the
constraints or one of the challenges
again in at least in my my mind when it
comes to service oriented architectures
or you know this emissaries 15 context
where you have multiple boundary
contacts is that oftentimes you have
business requirements that basically
require you to either sequence or kind
of orchestrate multiple Services
together so like for a classic one would
be like a transaction right so it would
be you need the order to be created as
well as the invent tree to be lowered
and and basically you want a
notification to be sent and you need a I
mean there are like three or four things
that you want to happen together and
then if one of them fails he wanted to
kind of all roll back and how is that
actually concept actually dealt with in
fifth terms and emissaries oh second
thank you this is a really really good
question so first off I want to say
something which I'm sure you know you
will know we all agree which is in the
world of loosely coupled systems or
distributed systems you know life in the
happy path is is beautiful
absolutely yeah
we know this right anytime something
breaks there's an error somewhere
debugging is a nightmare absolutely I
sometimes think you know some of the
devops roles in the SRE roles are paid
just because of that particular problem
because you know you can't make head or
tail of this thing where do you start
where do you stop right so the reason
again we liked we used the Emissary
mental model nickel was
to be able to think in terms of the
lowest level of abstraction of
communication which is a message
and and even that you know it could be a
one-way message could be a fire and
forget could actually be a request
response but still breaking it down to
the most fundamental which is just one
message
right and so this helped us to Think
Through then what is a conversation like
you said you know any kind of meaningful
business activity is going to be a
composition of multiple Services some
kind of an orchestration or even a
conversation if you will so being able
to map those lowest level first class
messages
and then be able to to Define to
delineate the orchestrations the
conversations helped us to Think Through
in terms of error handling and really
that was the primary sort of focus for
us was how can we make it easier it is
never going to be too easy of course we
know that but how do we make it easier
for the Developers for the application
Architects to be able to correlate
obviously correlation is a critical
piece here right how do you know this
error goes back to these three you know
so you know that right so so being able
to to deal with messaging at that level
of abstraction I think really was
pivotal otherwise if we had come top
down thinking through the orchestrations
then it's an all or nothing right you
have to think of rollback right roll
back in terms of the whole Mega
conversation whereas thinking in terms
of emissaries of messages
you can and oftentimes you do roll back
in terms of messages which is a lot less
expensive in terms of time in terms of
money and other other factors as opposed
to thinking of rollback as an All or
Nothing which in the wrong business
becomes extremely privately expensive
right
right this is an interesting idea so
essentially what you're saying as far as
I understand it is that we focus on
making sure that the messaging between
the services itself is sufficiently well
defined to be able to handle all the
error cases and then so that when you
actually have maybe a client that sends
a sequence of actions to be taken or you
call a meta service that calls multiple
other services there is enough
information in the responses to be able
to take corrective action in case of an
error
absolutely you're absolutely right to
think of a conversation as a composition
of messages
and rather than as a first-class Thing
by itself but really composition of
messages and like I said it helped us
that in terms of both the developer
abstraction the tooling but also in
terms of the conversation abstraction to
deal with it like you said to localize
it at the messaging level and our
thinking was if we can get the messaging
abstractions right then the developers
obviously and eventually you know you
have things like Fedora back in the days
orchestration Biz talk and SQL service
broker and so on which we're all dealing
with abstractions the higher level and
because the underlying infrastructure
more or less well defined it made our
life easier when we went on to build our
best talk or a service broker and
eventually things like Azure as well in
terms of orchestration yes so very good
summary thank you right okay so again
just to kind of push on that a little
bit more yes so obviously when you get
supposed to take a concrete example of
okay five actions need to be done right
in the sequence of one two three four
five and then you as a client I sent one
goes through two goes through three
fails four goes through and five doesn't
fails so you have two failures in
between right so as a client what was
the General thinking in terms of what is
the compensating actions to be taken
what's the general idea that okay you go
back and just individually roll back
each one of them in whichever way right
by maybe doing the opposite action of
what you were supposed to do or is there
was there kind of like some kind of
Common Thread that we could use to kind
of say yeah this particular set of
actions worked but these these others
did not so that kind of thing so was
there I mean I I can kind of see it from
the.net or SEO perspective that okay you
might think that hey that's that's one
level too high that's actually that's
the problem of the customer right it
problem of the business developer and it
varies by business so we provide the
tooling but they're on their own but I
was kind of like you know since you were
also heading patterns and practices I
was kind of like curious to see what
you're thinking on that was yes no thank
you you're right yes I'm certainly if
you liked patterns and practices I can
take some credit if you didn't like it I
can you can give me the blame as well I
spent many years yes building things
like Enterprise Library the cab and so
on but you mentioned a very interesting
uh concept there nikhil you spoke about
composition and I think you're right
right in terms of again another
abstraction that is so critical you know
to the underpinnings of services and
loose you know loose coupling and even
cloud-based is compensation being able
to compensate so I would say adding to
that is correlation so for us in terms
of being able to correlate whether it be
at the infrastructure level whether it
be at sort of the application Level or
even as you said at the business
component level
ensuring the tooling and the developer
experience for correlation was critical
in terms of compensation and you might
say this was a good or a bad idea but in
terms of compensation once again the
philosophical underpinning was based on
Ms arrays nickel was on messages be able
to say what are the boundaries of this
Emissary this message and think through
is this item potent for example what
happens if this guy shows up twice right
how do you do you deal with it or the
guy doesn't show up at all then what do
you deal with it right be able to
compensate at that level maybe it was a
little bit of us taking the easy way out
because you know at that level like you
said you could Define you can prescribe
and you can enforce but of course as you
go up these abstraction in terms of
applications it gets you know more and
more challenging and certainly much much
more convoluted but we felt like if we
could establish the boundaries the
barriers at that level at least then
there was a solid footing a solid
infrastructure which I think in
retrospect you know we can debate let us
the right or the wrong approach
absolutely yeah I mean like they say
right hindsight is 20 20 and I'm sitting
here and I'm sitting here in 2022 and
critiquing things that were built into a
2000 right so it's a long time ago yes
so I'm not actually at the end of the
day it worked really well right I mean
the proof of the pudding is in the
eating and Microsoft is a Microsoft is a
trillion dollar company for obvious
reasons right so one aspect also
traditionally one of the usual arguments
that one some people bring up when you
talk about service oriented I mean loose
coupling and service oriented stuff
versus monoliths right is that well
monoliths they say it's simply faster
right because everything is in the same
memory space you're calling things
immediately and it returns very fast so
given that you're kind of like using
this for something like Azure which is
is a infrastructure core storage and
compute and all of that did you ever
worry about the performance aspect and
is that how did that kind of no it's a
again a really really good question they
could absolutely no you're right you can
certainly argue you can make the case
and probably it started true in in a
good number of scenarios use cases but
actually where single system monoliths
you know in terms of response time
possibly latency could certainly be much
much more responsive than perhaps a
Loosely coupled system that is a
composition of services absolutely the
two bets that drove our thinking firstly
was that in terms of bandwidth in terms
of latency that you know it was going to
be a game where connectivity is gonna
was going to improve in Leaps and Bounds
it was going to be less and less of a
challenge over time which again we can
discuss you know obviously that's right
or wrong the second thing was whilst the
cost the expense in terms of the a
single transaction versus
the cost of maintaining and upgrading
and versioning these systems obviously
with a single system monolith as we know
being able to to version to upgrade to
to maintain obviously the whole thing
may have to come down stop for some time
you know and the dependencies because
just being able to trace through the
dependencies across the set of
components objects classes versus having
very well defined boundaries and being
able to say look I'm going to move
version this system which is critical
for us in terms of thinking through the
early Cloud infrastructure because we
just could not stop it right and of
course you could argue in fact that this
actually is a good segue in terms of
blockchain based architectures because
and this might be controversial but I'll
say it anyway right much of what the
blockchain world calls decentralized
really nickel is Federated
right most of this world is not really
decentralized right it is actually to be
polite to be nice to them you can say
it's Federated and what is Federated
it's basically you know a Loosely
coupled collection of systems that are
cooperating towards obviously so again
it's a fine line but I realized
basically this evolution in terms of to
your point the the cost the expenses of
consuming versus the cost the expense of
of upgrading because yeah as an
architect right when people say you know
what is a good architecture obviously
there are many ways you can slice and
dice it but for me the how you measure
architecture Nicholas uh how evolvable
is it
right and of course the economics of
evolvability are critical right you can
obviously teach anything but but being
able to evolve in an economically
feasible viable manner is how I Define
architecture so for us this notion of
being able to evolve this system of
services almost independently those
benefits significantly outweigh any with
respect to like you said the potential
of decreasing perhaps you know response
times latency because the BET like we
made is that technology is going to
improve connectivity bandwidth obviously
and it's still obviously still very much
improving right yeah yeah yeah it's a
good point so since you brought up
blockchains right there's this one
question that I had and then basically
maybe you can clear it when you talk
about you know fifth terms and
emissaries and all it's this this whole
kind of it gives you this mental picture
of medieval Europe and
kingdoms and all of that and there is in
blockchains is also this concept called
the Byzantine consensus in general
General problem are they in any way
related or is this is this kind of like
just a flight of fancy in my mind
no no so look you are the first
person who has made this connection I'll
tell you
you're the owner okay who's asked here
so then obviously it's a flight of fancy
in my mind
so yes because Byzantine fault tolerance
you know Byzantine like you said is a
collection of generals and and the
question is how do they cooperate right
because they don't trust each other and
the notion of victims was basically
there was a lack of trust or zero trust
if you will or some degrees of trust so
you're absolutely right that the bft
which by the way you know is quite
prevalent these days in terms of
blockchain based systems goes back very
much the same or similar mental model of
victims and emissaries of course in
terms of of the I would say the fifth
term model the question was more around
how do we ensure we have the
abstractions for constructive
collaboration whereas in the Byzantine
scenario it's more a question of there
is no trust and how do they even get to
some level of consensus with respect to
anything is being the focus of bft but
you're absolutely right and I'm glad you
because you're the first and the only
person who has been the connection as
far as I know thank you
yeah cool I mean I think I've kind of
covered and I think we've had a
discussion about most of the topics that
I had wanted to talk about in this
episode do you have any things do you
feel that there's anything that I missed
that you would like to just talk about
before we close thank you legal first of
all I want to say thank you look it's
been that you know a true pleasure to be
able to discuss the philosophical
underpinnings if you will of azure
of.net and to go through the the
abstractions then because oftentimes
these are forgotten or glossed over in
terms of the only thing if if I might
add would be I believe and this is more
of a conviction uh that much of the
ideas we discussed in terms of loose
coupling composition the notion of fief
terms or Byzantine generals and
emissaries or agents also applies I
think at the economic level now we
discussed about the infrastructure and
the application architecture level I
believe that more and more Enterprises
need to think through
an economic architecture they lack that
today
I think in three years in five years we
will see Enterprises have an economic
architecture and I think the concepts
very much drive those as well so I would
say it's the only thing that perhaps you
know we could talk about some other time
but this notion of Enterprise economic
architectures is very close to my heart
and that's the last piece I would say of
the puzzle in terms of my own thinking
thank you for that John I think that was
a great end to the episode and leave
them wanting more as they say on
economic architectures I had a great
time talking to you John thank you legal
a true privilege and a pleasure actually
so thank you for the wonderful questions
that I I look forward to having more
discussions so once again very grateful
for the for the time I know you're a
very busy man and very grateful for this
window of time so thank you sure no
worries
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcasts including other episodes
visit our website at sc.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this in all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening